David Soares Batista

Personal Data

PLACE AND DATE OF BIRTH: Lisbon, January 4th, 1981

PHONE: +49 (0)1523 850 98 89 (mobile)

EMAIL: dsbatista@inesc-id.pt

HOMEPAGE: http://davidsbatista.github.io

SUMMARY

I like to explore and extract knowledge from large volumes of data, be it structured or unstructured, numbers or text. I'm experienced in Natural Language Processing (NLP), Information Retrieval (IR), Machine Learning (ML) and Big-Data.

In the past I've worked in projects, tackling problems with a strong text-mining and text-analysis components, involving tasks such as information extraction, classification, clustering and information retrieval.

In 2016, I successfully defended my Ph.D., proposing new methods to perform semantic relationship extraction from large collections of documents.

Professional Experience

Jan. 2016 - Present

Data Engineer @ HelloFresh AG (http://www.hellofresh.de)

- Text analysis of customer NPS comments with NLP and ML.
- Data Warehousing and processes automation for data analysis.
- Design, build and maintain ETLs and infrastructure for batch processing.
- Technologies: Python NLTK, scikit-learn, Spark, Hive, Impala, Airflow.

Jun. 2011 – Apr. 2014

NLP/ML Researcher @ INESC-ID (http://www.inesc-id.pt)

 $\label{eq:project:REACTION - Computational Journalism} Project: REACTION - Computational Journalism$

- Named Entity Recognition and Disambiguation over news articles.
- Semantic Relationship Extraction between named-entities.
- Topic Modeling (i.e., LDA) techniques applied to on-line news.
- Analysis of large graphs connecting entities and topics.

Oct. 2009 - Oct. 2011

NLP/ML Researcher @ LaSIGE (http://www.lasige.di.fc.ul.pt) Project: GREASE - Geographic Reasoning for Search Engines

- Language identification on a web-crawl using n-grams models.
- Disambiguation of geographic ambiguous names in Portuguese text.
- Alignment between geo-ontologies by linking geographical references.

Oct. 2007 - Jul. 2008

Software Developer @ Nokia Siemens Networks

- Development of data collection modules for a GSM monitoring system.
- Technologies: Java, CORBA Architecture, Oracle RDBMS

Computer Skills

Programming: Python, Java, Shell Scripting
Machine Learning: scikit-learn, gensim, MinorThird

Natural Language Processing: Python NLTK, Stanford CoreNLP, LingPipe

Distributed Computing: Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Impala

Information Retrieval: Apache Lucene/Solr

Databases/NoSQL: MySQL, PostgreSQL, REDIS

EDUCATION

2011 - 2015

Doctor of Philosphy (Ph.D.) Instituto Superior Técnico, University Lisbon.

"Large-Scale Semantic Relationship Extraction"

To achieve scalable relationship extraction, I proposed using an on-line classifier, based on the idea of nearest neighbor classification, and leveraging min-hash and locality sensitive hashing for efficient similarity search. To obtain training data, for the classifier, I proposed a bootstrapping technique relying on distributional word representations.

2007-2009

Master's Degree (M.Sc.) - Faculty of Sciences, University of Lisbon. "Geographic Text Mining"

I developed an information extraction system based on Conditional Random Fields to generate geographic summaries. The summary lists the geographic entities found in a document and mapped into geographic concepts in a geographic ontology. The system was applied to a crawl of the Portuguese Web (25GB raw text) using a Hadoop cluster.

2003-2007

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Informatics Engineering, Faculty of Sciences, University Lisbon.

2005-2006, Karlsruhe Universität (TH), Germany

• Erasmus exchange student for two semesters

2004 November - 2005 July - IT support (part-time) @ University of Lisbon

 \bullet Troubleshooting network connections and services, preventative maintenance, helping and educating new users.

2003 NOVEMBER - 2004 MARCH - SysAdmin (part-time) @ University of Lisbon

• Administration and configuration of networking software and services (e.g., samba, backups, quotas, mail, web, crontab, IPTables).

LANGUAGES

PORTUGUESE: Native Speaker

English: Spoken: Fluent Written: Fluent

GERMAN: Spoken: Good Written: Fair Certification: Goethe-Zertifikat B.1

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Semi-Supervised Bootstrapping of Relationship Extractors with Distributional Semantics. David S Batista, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In *Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing-EMNLP'15.* - Honorable Mention for Best Short Paper

A Minwise Hashing Method for Addressing Relationship Extraction from Text. David S Batista, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In Web Information Systems Engineering-WISE'13.

Exploring DBpedia and Wikipedia for Portuguese Semantic Relationship Extraction David Soares Batista, David Forte, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J. Silva. *Linguamática*, 5(1), 2013.

Toponym Disambiguation using Ontology-based Semantic Similarity David S Batista, João D Ferreira, Francisco M Couto, and Mário J Silva. In *Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language* 2012.

A Statistical Study of the WPT05 Crawl of the Portuguese Web David Batista and Mário J. Silva. In *In FALA 2010 VI Jornadas en Tecnología del Habla and II Iberian SLTech Workshop* Universidade de Vigo, 2010.

Geographic Signatures for Semantic Retrieval David S Batista, Mário J Silva, Francisco M Couto, and Bibek Behera. In *Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Geographic Information Retrieval* ACM, 2010.